so its time to move on to the next talk
this talk has the keynote speech
by Eric Allman
Chief Science Officer
of Sendmail
and I think that internet mail past present and bit of future
I will introduce
his biography
Eric Allman is the original author of Sendmail and
longtime contributor to partial index
he also wrote ending lock roads C-twelve lock identification
beside external Sendmail he has worked with database management
systems and
and neural
network based speech recognition
system administration and networking
he is chief science officer and co-founder of
Sendmail
incorporated
before joining Sendmail
he served as CEO
for Swift
inc. which is now part of 247 Media Inc.
he was with the lovern
and provided the whole scale research software infrastructure
for most of the projects at University of Berkeley
he has contributed as senior
at the international computer science institute
to neural network systems and
ihe was also part
of Ingress
invasion of system
and only co-authored the advisor for
Unix magazine and was a member of
the board of directors at Unix association
he has currently program chair
for the conference on e-mail and spam and
member of ACM Queue editorial board
and the board of
trustee of call performances
he holds a Master of science degree in
computer science from University of California Berkeley
so please
make sure, can everyone hear me clearly?
okay. I'm going to give you a little bit of
well actually quite a bit of history about
e-mail and related technologies starting
really from
before the internet existed
this talk that I gave a couple of years
ago and although there's a lot of slides I'm going to
try and go through it fairly quickly because the
more interesting
current stuff is
towards the end. The current stuff will be
some observations about spam
and e-mail security in general
and the authentication and reputation which is
what I've been working on most recently
then I'm going to give you some everyone always
wants to know what I think will be the future
of e-mail and I always tell them I don't know
any better than they do but they insist on
having me tell them so I'll come up with a few
things there
I've thrown in some stuff by the way about
some other things that people have asked me
about here so I'm
trying to adjust the talk to be
of
interest to
what people seem to want to hear
so first I want to talk about the
prehistory of
of the internet really this is the Arpanet
starting from zero hosts
on the network to two hundred and thirteen which
is where the Arpanet
peaked out it couldn't go much larger than
two hundred thirteen because
there was only an eight bit
host address
I
I'm going to talk, plotting things on this kind of graph
this is date down at the bottom and the number of
hosts on the side
this is a one year scale. I'll keep readjusting the
scale as we move up
otherwise this is just a flat line down at the bottom
so yes you can
so this is kind of one thing to start of
the history of e-mail
but it turns out this is
about an awful lot of things I just want to
read you a quote
that describes this event in December
well
on December 9, 1968 Dirk Engelbar
who by the way who invented the computer mouse
and with a group of seventeen researchers
working with him in the augmentation
research center at Stanford research institute
in Menlo Park, California
presented a ninety-minute live public demonstration
of the on-line system nls
that they'd been working on since 1962
the public presentation was a session of the
fall short of computer conference hall at
the convention center in San Francisco
and was attended by about one thousand computer
professionals
this was the public
debut of the computer mouse
but the mouse of the only one of many innovations
demonstrated that day including hypertext, object
address and dynamic file linking
as well as shared screen collaboration involving
two persons of different sites
communicating over a network with audio and
video interface
Okay imagine that day
no network exists
at all
and they're doing a remote demo with
audio and video
they're interacting doing screen sharing
over the internet, they're showing off the mouse for
the first time that nobody's ever seen
and he throws in stuff like hypertext and what not
I can only wish I was there that must have been amazing
the point I made of course is that
back in 1968
they were demoing stuff that we only
recently got on the internet
we havent really come that far
so in September 1969
the first Arpanet
was
brought up, September second nineteen sixty nine to be
precise which happens to be my birthday
that was a single host at UCLA
which is a little odd because you think of most
networks as having at least two hosts on them
but
for a while there was actually only one host on the Arpanet
this is a very smudged map of the original Arpanet
they had this thing called the IMP the
Internet Message Processor
which was essentially the routers that
but they
gather the data around the
Arpanet which wasn't particularly difficult
in this case but
it became so later and then a
single host which was a Sigma 7. this is obviously
by the way somebody's hand drawn
slide that was done with those ink that gets
easily smudged when you
put your inside of your hand on it
so fortunately
that one host
a month added at SRI
university of California Santa barbara and
the university of Utah
which gave us a map like this
so you can see
the round things here are the IMPs there's
four of them
and each one of them has exactly one host
hanging off of it
you could have up to four hosts connected to a single IMP
so kind of a mini star topology.
this is actually very important look at this
because it's already
an arbitrary
networks topology. its not a star configuration
its not a ring configuration
its essentially arbitrary
hookup
and that actually
is something that we had
that industry had to rediscover as well
the other thing
that knows is that there is
Magnium three sixteen
a Sigma 7, an XDS nine fourteen
and a PDP ten there were no
two identical architectures on the first
Arpanet
it was designed right from the start to
be headed off tramps
this was untrue of
any network that you saw
up until
any other network
for example
Microsoft networks always assume you're running
windows
on the program
hardware
the Arpanet had a totally different view
now here's just kind of a humor
picture did
this is John Pasto sorry it's not very good
Steve Carcker
and Vint Cert
I have no idea what the pickles are
about
but I do think it's interesting that here
are probably the three people who were
but fathers of the internet
and they couldn't even get it right
they've got outputs connected to outputs and inputs to inputs
so wasn't
all that long
before the network was quite a bit bigger
this has gone cross country now
we should point out
these links
were really really fast data links
fifty six kilobytes per second
and they cost a fortune
so fact
that they started off in one little cluster
together on the west coast was just to
save costs as much as anything
but by September they had spread out
quite a bit now
the Arpanet was designed
to
share expensive resources
so
lots of universities wanted to have their
own computer
but computers were too expensive
so they could put in
small machines
that could
you could connect to the larger machines with
over the net
and so the two primary protocols of the time
were Telnet and FTP
e-mail was not
even considered
in the original design of the Arpanet
what do the
teams
mean the teams in minor. those were
they're called tips they were
essentially
access
if you will smart
well not very smart notes. they weren't actually
computers they were places you could log in
be it just a terminal if you will
so you know being an IMP
they had no
computer there on the network that they could
log into the other places
that's fundamentally it
okay
so in late nineteen seventy one was one of
the first network e-mail
was sent if you're going to tell first ever
in all of history
it was sent by this guy Ray Thompson who
was indeed the real father of e-mail
people sometimes try and make me out to be
that but it just isn't true
he really is
he was working
at
Bolt Beranek and Newman which was one of the
contractors on the Arpanet
the original version was just
part of FTP. he did a file transfer
and the
special semantics were
it would just depend whatever you had out of
the end of some fixed file so each person
would have an Inbox
and it would go splat
and add your text to the end of their
mailbox I don't think it had headers at the top
it was in late 1971 and it
linked two machines that were creatively named
the BBNA and BBNB
there they are the first two e-mail notice
that they're sitting right next to each
other
the first e-mail was not sent around the world
or anything like that. it stayed within a single
room
these are PEP temps by the way
just as an aside now really eleven seventy
one Unix one dot oh came out
that was done by these folks Ken Thompson
and Dennis Richie
Unix 1.0 wasn't particularly interesting
from network point of view but
we all know what
eventually happened to
Unix I'm kind of putting this into a historic
context
so let's go to 1973 it was
the beginning of a really really exciting
time at Berkeley, not
not entirely because that was the year I entered
Berkeley but
that was one of the reasons
and at the same time there were people
running around like this guy Bill Joy who had a lot to do with
Berkeley NX
and this guy who's out there somewhere
you cannot have a better picture
If I had a picture of him from that your era
he's actually leaning down next to a truck
that said
that said weak detection unit on it
but it was only a little tiny then so I didn't take that.
This was another guy
another grad student
we always thought he was kind of arrogant because
he said his goal was to be
the CEO of a major corporation which we thought was
not something we could
plan for. He is now CEO Google
after being CEO Novell on
well I'm
Chee had I only
gone to his school
so as a result of these and a lot of other
very creative people that were just a huge number
of people that ended up at Berkeley all at the
same time
you seemed to be really excited about this Unix stuff
they came up with
what's now known as Berkeley NX
so first Bill who did the Berkeley software distributions that were quite literally
just a mad tape
and
because of various licensing reasons the
best he could do
couldn't really even legally label the tape
he put a label out that said this is a tape of this
and turned it in
this is the first Beastie mascot
drawing. this is out of order. this dint
actually come until later
this was
done by a guy who worked with Sam Lefller
who was also one of the Berkeley guys
at Pixar
his name is John Lassiter
and as you know he now runs Disney corporation
so he owns the original art which is probably
worth a fortune then
so moving along
Merkle puzzles
now Merkle puzzles
probably most of you
have never even heard of
a guy named Ralph Merkle
graduate student at Berkeley
submitted a proposal
for a paper for CS two forty four
which was rejected
because it was
an obviously absurd idea
it was in fact the basis for public key encryption
and
without public key encryption
any kind of authentication and global encryption
was completely impractical because before
that all we had was symmetric keys
so if there were
in people on the
network
and you need to exchange with them you needed n squared
copies of keys all over the place and that
you just couldn't deal with that as n got
you know to really large numbers like a
hundred
so the other thing was encryption was still
classified by the US government as a munition
which means it wasn't legal
to export it to other countries
and even back then there were starting to
be is substantial amount of international
involvement with
Unix and other such systems
so
in
April of 1977 the RSA algorithm was finally
published. this of course is the
one that everyone knows about as the work
is directly
based on Merkle's work
so I think 1977
as we see that the networks gotten quite
a bit larger
this was
pretty close to its peak I think
actually still its bigger
the pink loans and pink sounds
by the way
when i say different architectures
16 bit words
36 bit words 60 bit words
what else do I have
up here? just all kinds of things are even some machines
that have
twenty bit words ten bit bytes
and somehow they've managed to make that work
there's a couple of interesting things on here they have
so satellite links to Hawaii and to
Norway
and so the network had gone international
sort of
I say sort of because
it was going to a US
air force base I think in
Norway so
was still considered a military thing at that
point
so
the non-US citizens weren't supposed to have
access to it
UUCP got published
in 1978
it brought
network access of the sort to universities
that didn't have to darker contracts which were
I've hard to get
and by the way getting an Arpanet link was
very expensive so you pretty much
needed to have a darker sponsor which
is to be able to afford it
in May of 1978 the
first ever spent was sent on the
Arpanet. at the time it was a DEC salesman
and
I'll tell you more about what he did
shortly
late 1979
was the appearance of Usenet
which was based originally on UUCP although
could easily work over the Arpanet
this made it was the predecessor of
what we would now call forums and blogs and
things like that
but most importantly it made flame words possible
and then
finally
in September 1979 UCB
got an Arpanet nose. they actually had the one before
but it had then shut down because the
the guy who ran it
was told that he had failed to demonstrate
that his
research was going to enable them to build
smarter bombs
literally i saw the letter
but by
this point
the group I was working on INGREs
got that link
we were database management
system and of course the government was very
interested in data bases
and in particular distributed databases
we didn't have a very big
grasp so we had a whopping 9600 baud
link to the Arpanet. this is for all of campus
actually it was for
CS division
which was not all of campus but
you know the folks some of the departments
didn't have a clue what a network was
but everyone in the CS division wanted
access to the Arpanet
of course because it was the newest shiny bling thing
to have and everyone
had to get there
well we had a PDP-11
that really could handle that many simultaneous
logins much less
the ports that were expensive at the time
to put this into perspective we had a PDP-11 seventy
that had a one point five micro
second cycle time so substantially less than one minute
the 16-bit word and we have
a lot of memory we had a 196K of memory
on the system
we would have to put
a DH-11 ports
another
this is a port multiplex where you get 16 words
cost about 4700 dollars so
about 300 dollars
per port which doesn't sound like much
but remember
that's like 1,000 dollars per port today
so
well I have to show off
some things this is a PDP 11 seventy.this
is what computers are supposed to look like
unlike what they are today
they had switches and lights and
all kinds of cool things and dials. Ah it was great so
we had
we were what we're able to do was
release two TT white ports three hundred
baud TT white ports
to be shared among everyone in the computer
science division
at Berkeley
probably about
fifty people well
forty professors. there were
other students but we just said no you know
still
can't handle it can't possibly do that
but professors could have their
computer
terminal sorry in their office
and they had a line that ran into the-mail room
and there was a plug board
he could
put in the patch code between your office
and whatever computer you want to have access
to and there were two those
for the Arpanet machine which was the
machine I was
working on then
and of course people would come along
they want access to the Arpanet. they just
unplug
one of the cables that was in there and plug in theirs
there were professors having screaming matches
at each other in the hallways and it
probably came to fisticuffs at some point
and of course they all came to me and wanted
me to fix the problem
I wasn't it and I don't know how they thought
I was going to fix the problem
which I was an undergraduate then I don't know how they
thought I was gonna fix the problem. What I did however was
observe what they really wanted was not access to the
Arpanet like FTP and
Telnet
what they want
was e-mail.Email was the killer rap
even back then
we had something called Berknet that linked our
internal machines
using RS 232 lines of
9600 baud this is written by
a guy named Eric Schmidt yes the very same Eric Schmidt
who is now CEO of Google and he's a better
CEO than he is a coder
but it worked
as it turns out we also had a UUCP connection
which ran from the main department machine
which
was a VAX OM 780 call Ernie CoVAX
and so I wrote something called deliver mail
deliver mail was just
a quick hack to forward
messages between networks it dint have time to
anything like fixing headers or
anything like that
so it was a disaster in some sense waiting to happen
well it got the professors off of my back
so as far as I was concerned it was a success
It got released in four
point zero what
is now four zero BSD which is four BSD at the time
in 1980 and much to my shock it turned out to be
very popular Berkeley
was not unique lots and lots of places
have this problem
and so there is deliver mail on the chart
now you can see this is
pretty much
toward the end of the Arpanet era
the Arpanet
geographically now looks
like this
the circles by the way were exploded in the other
material that I had but I dint want to
give you all of that but
there is several satellite link now
there's a direct satellite link to London that's
still at Hawaii link
and so forth
if you look carefully you will see the
main
university
military and military contractors sites
that's all of them. Sizemo I don't
know if Sizemo had an Arpanet link I don't think
they did although they could have
it would have been in here somewhere so
I think that came later
let's put it this way
we Berkeley ended up being the gateway between
the UUCP and the Arpanet
cos it didn't take people long to figure out
a route-mail
you're there you had to do it manually but
it could be done
I will have a comment about that later
so let's continue on to the next phase
by 1981 through 1988
this goes from 213 hosts
that were on
the Arpanet to 3300
hosts in seven years
so we'll start with our usual graph
this was when I started first putting SMTP on a Sendmail
worked on Sendmail before because things
like header writing
was becoming a real problem. you couldn't reply to addresses.
everyone you had to be
to be a guru in order to
figure out how to address things there
was even an entire book
put up
that described
how to do addressing
but
Berkeley got a contract
to do the
base
platform operating system platform to support darker
research they had all of these
diverse machines
but they discovered that that made it really
hard for research projects to share work with
each other so they decided that there would
be a standard platform it would be the VAX
running Berkeley Unix
and one of things they needed was an SMTP server
is by the way I haven't said anything about
SMTP being published it wasn't published
and I was working on up very early drafts
and what happened was Bill Joy asked me
random data base not Sendmail
Bill Joy came up to me and said
you know would you do this
and
in a moment of weakness said sure how hard
can it be
25 years later I'm telling you who
it is
harder than it looks
and
few months later
4.1a which was technically test
release
came out with Sendmail
SMTP which also have
the first networks that
so
this is
Berkeley Unix on the internet
except the internet doesn't exist yet
sort of exists. there is this test platform but the
world still using Arpanet
finally about a year after I started implementing
SMTP the specs were
published
after
it's been shipped
its an internet tradition
by the way
January 1st 1983
was the flag day it was just called the flag day
that was the day that
the government said we're going to turn off
the Arpanet
and they literally just said
we're going to send out a message into all the IMPs
to stop forwarding packets
and if you're not on the internet by then
you're going to lose your network connectivity
and there were a whole bunch of people who
said yeah yeah they're bluffing and guess what
they lost their network connectivity
but Berkeley was there we didn't
so
that was cool
in September of 1983 the same year
a 4.2 BSD shipped
this was kind of the basis for
at least from the user interface
was the basis for
Unix as we know it today
so it had all the network and
stuff and
at that point
we were able to track down John Lasetter and
have him do an update
and does it seem much more important at the
time so
here's Beastie in color with the attractive green
tennis shoes and so forth
once again for historic context I have to
run in some things
in 1985 there was a company actually
did some more research it was originally called
control video corporation changed his name
to quantum computer services
an year later that changed its name to
America Online
they had the walled garden they had an e-mail
only among other AOL subscribers they
weren't connected to the internet
in any
any sense
this is really important
may 1987 a guy named Rick
Adams who worked in Sizemo
went off and started the first commercialized PE
there was apparently another one that started
on exactly the same day so the two people
get to fight each other over who was first
the difference is that UUNET turned into one of
the largest pieces
in the world and the other one didn't
so
this was the first time that you could
get access to the internet without being
a government
government-sponsored
so that's a big deal
so of next chunk of history we'll take from
1988 to 1993 at this point
I'm going in about
ten x
both on the internet just in progress graphs
pretty clear
so
this was kind of the first security incidents
on the internet the internet worm
It was written by Grampston in a Harvard and who
probably should have flunked out because he
didn't understand commentary growth
and he really thought that this thing would run
quietly on the internet and first of
all there was a bug in his
program
so it didn't kill itself off as it was supposed
to and
he didn't understand that if each machine infects 4 machines
that's a really large
power
not a small one
but it did make people start to think for
the first time about
security on the internet up until the internet had
been kind of
a very collegiate
atmosphere
you had to be to be on the internet you had to
be a researcher to get on it
if you wanted an account on somebody else's
machine to be good all you do is they can
I had an account and go sure give you an
account
so security dint seem all that important but
this made it clear that
it was
March 1989 in fact exactly
30 years ago this past Friday two days
ago
Tim Berners-Lee proposed what
we now know as the world wide web
he did a prototype browser that was published
in October
of 1990
and but that one kind of disappeared it
was more concerned
research
organization in Switzerland
so there's Tim
I think that was not
contemporary. I think he had more hair when he
proposed it
okay
we had the internet
and that allowed
non
government people to get access to the net
but the backbone of the internet was still run
by the national science foundation getting transferred
from
the military
over to
non military government funding but it
was still
funded
and their rules that an acceptable use policy
that said no commercial traffic
so UUNET customers could
run commercial traffic to each other but they
could write to other people. there wasn't any chance
that would run over these wires
that effectively said
you can't use the internet for commercial
purposes at all
CIX
which then stood for commercial internet
exchange was where the various
largish ISP were started to be regional.
there was one on the west coast and one
on the east coast and one of the southeast
and
so forth said
we're all going to run wires together into one room
we're going to put a big router there and we're
going to be able to exchange traffic with us
without ever going over an SF net
because we're not allowed commercial traffic
and they essentially said cut the government
out of the equation which was great as that's what
the government wanted anyway
so
1991 July was the first
time he could really use the internet for
anything commercial
1992 a multipurpose internet
mail extensions was published a USENET
conference
and this allowed embedding something other
than plain text
into
e-mail messages notably at the time it was
used for
pictures or graphs and
things like that there was discussion about
maybe
maybe some day we could
do sound and possibly way way way in the distant future
we may be able to think about video but
it was really just pictures
okay 1993 through 1996 is
taking us from one point three million to
to almost thirteen million
February of 1993 NCSA mosaic was released
this is the national center
for super computer applications at the university
of Illinois
Champane Urbana
it's the first broadly used
browser and in fact
was the direct descendant
sorry the
direct parent of
Netscape
and Mozilla and so forth all kind
of goes back to NCSA mosaic
now Sendmail had been
I had abandoned Sendmail for a number
of years because I've gone to work for start-up
and
they seem to want action work on what I was
being paid for
and
Sendmail had diverged
and so there were many versions of it. some of them
had some good ideas some of them some not
so good
ideas
every vendor
like DEC and HP and IBM and so forthhad their own
proprietary version of Sendmail
and you couldn't really share things between them and
I came along and I came
back to the university
first a lot of these things and that a lot
of other things all of these things is the
Sendmail 8 which is
the Sendmail which
pretty much still exists to this day
that was
way more successful than I had
anticipated
and
that turned into a problem
later as we'll see
Netscape was founded
in 1994
Mark Reasen was one of the principles
in that and he essentially left
NCSA took the source code with him and co
founded the company
the green code spam anyone remember the greencode spam?
now I mentioned
there was the first spam
earlier
but it wasn't really a spam
as i said the network previously largely cooperative
you know had flame wars but they were
mostly innocent
could be dealt with
turns out that spam was not new. the first electronically
transmitted
commercial
message
was in September 13th 1904
using the telegraph
so advertisers had figured out this new
technology was going to be someplace they
could thrive
the first
e-mail spam was this DEC salesman
who DEC had released a new
part of the computer and decided that
he really want all of its customers to know
about this
so he sent
an e-mail message
with copying every single customer
did he had
well it turns out the-mail programs of the
time they thought about having
you know three or four may be ten recipients
on a message
not a thousand
and so it broke the-mail system broke
all kinds of things
but I don't really cannot this is the first
spam because he said gee I didn't know
he apologized
well he wasn't trying to do anything malicious.
he genuinely thought that
his customers would want to know about this
new machine
there is also a 1988 a chain letter
called make money fast it was
a pyramid scheme
But it wasn't
really technically a spam either
but we're definitely seeing the greed
is good attitude coming to
the internet much to do
disgust of a lot of us
and they call a nation was two lawyers and
from Texas Canter and Siegel
who
advertise in technically Usenet
not e-mail
they sent every single
news group
the same posting
offering to sign people up for a price for
the green card lottery which was so people
non-residents could work in the US
they didn't tell you that you could sign yourself
up for free
but if you gave them money they'd be happy to
do for you what you could do for free
and they were completely unapologetic about
this they said wait a minute here we have
the right
to do this
they even published a book
on how to spam
and they made a ton of money off of that book too
I believe that brought them this far by
the way and have
gone into
you know
very long
April 1994 Webcaller was the
first full text
Webcaller
and was the beginning of search engines as
we know them today
the first
well this is pseudo liar as good a time as
virus was an e-mail message that went around
saying
it's
the subject was good times it said
there's a virus running around the network
if you even open that message
it will trash your machine you know the message because
it has the subject good times
forward this to everyone you know
the warning was itself
the virus
and it was tremendously effective I had to
spend
about two days calming down people about this
just saying no
don't forward it
the
as I have said so
earlier Sendmail 8 was very very
successful
so successful that I really couldn't support
it myself anymore
just because untenable so
I formed a Sendmail consortium was which was
a group of volunteers that helped do this in 1995
and later 1995 SMIME was published
this was the first attempt to do
but it actually wasn't the first it was the
best known to this day attempt to do
encryption and authentication in e-mail
that
back book was published
I don't remember
exactly when but it was in 1994
right in this time frame
this is 1996 to 2000
from about thirty million two hundred nine
million hosts
Hotmail was founded. I thought this was insane
at the time which is why I don't
you know I'm not filthy rich right now
Hotmail
it had access to the internet so I said well
of course you've already got a mailbox they
gave you free-mail boxes
and it took off
like mad it was crazy
in
Microsoft said hey wait a minute maybe this
internet thing isn't going to go away after
all
and we should get in on it
and so they put a very bad
SMTP gateway into exchange
they slapped the network onto their existing
worker tools which
were not designed for a hostile environment
at all
they did no consideration whatsoever of securing
and just dropped a huge number of people on
the internet
essentially naked and unprotected
and we're still
dealing with this to this day
the only thing that was
impressive about this was Microsoft
in a very short period of time was able to
completely redefine the company
as an internet company and
much faster than anyone had thought possible
Yahoo was founded in
October ninety seven
we all know about that
a Microsoft acquired hot mail
they were able to do it as fast as they wanted
the rumor
unconfirmed is that they paid 400
million dollars
for this company that was barely over a year
old and had something like ten employees
quite a coop
in March of 1998 I and a friend of mine
co-founded Sendmail Inc.
Sendmail
even with the help of the consortium
was still stuck with research problems and
so we said we can commercialize this
here's a very well read picture of the
initial
people in the company and two of us
are still there
now into the virus era March of 1999
Melissa there was an Outlook
macrovirus
was a hypersoft
was really kind of
a worm as much as it was a virus
in January 2000 the
government finally relaxed the encryption policy
finally admitted it
that everyone outside the US had encryption
anyway
and so we might as well be able to play in
the game
with the rest of the world
we immediately put
encryption TLS encryption into Sendmail
all in fact we've already had it implemented
but we couldn't release it
and so
this came out we
pushed out the version that already had
TLS
what we wanted to do was had the government
changed its mind we had to be too late
so we dot to that really fast but they didn't change their
minds but the they may have changed
not change their mind because they've realized
it was
two weeks later it's too late
in March of 2000 we
released an interface called Milter
this is
a way to do
plugins into Sendmail that allow you to do email filtering
was specifically designed for anti-spam
the MTA market changed a lot back then or
essentially not the market
the world had been about reliability and
getting
mail from A to B without losing it
and around here was when spam was getting
so bad people said no we need to do is not
forward
anything that
might be
problematic
and
April
2000 the I love you virus this is a
Visual Basic virus he had to
click on it but it's turns out that people
couldn't resist clicking on
a text that's called I love you
they were sad what can I say
2001 to the Present
well we've gone from that
hundred ten thousand roughly up to
about four hundred forty million
well as of the last survey I could find
well let's see let's start off with an unequivocal
the virus it was kind of one of the symbols
up Postfix which was a competitor to
Sendmail was released
Postfix was actually really good
alternative and Lisa and I when he was writing
Postfix we would exchange a lot of email
talking but I talked with him at one point
before it was released
and taken surely say much longer than
he expected
I said i asked him how the-mail was going and
he said
well its taken longer than I thought that's
that's harder than it looks isn't it
the it's been an exercise in humility
so you think that I hate him because he's
competitor of Sendmail but
no hes one of the good guys
the SPR project which was one of the first
attempt to do e-mail authentification
in one sense or another start up
in
also you know oh three was the Sobig.F virus.
It was the largest
attack
on today using something called .div files
program information files
as attachment
it was significant because it contained
it's own SMTP engine
up until then
things have been
piggybacking on exchange so submitting
mail as though you were users submitting from
Outlook
this one
had
SMTP engine optimized for
sending out trash
It had adaptive context so it kept changing itself
so it was harder to find fingerprints and self-destructed
on a particular day. so something
automated to just kind of disappear
on one day
I don't think anybody knows why
all sort working on domain keys which is a another
technology for the authentication.I'll talk
about that SPF later
the MyDoom virus came out it was even
spread faster was even bigger than
sobig
it's big innovation was that it used network as
well as e-mail
and it was specifically designed to infect
machines to use them as spam engine so arguably
this was the beginning of Zombie farms
In February 2004
Microsoft announces sender id which was
really kind of SPF with
synthetic sure
and in December of four DKIM work began. DKIM was
an extension of the domain keys
there were some experience with domain keys
we realize that there were some things that
needed too
have improved and so far I was very much involved
in the DKIM work
so that's
unfortunately the five years I've been working
on this stuff now
and
the actual DKIM based sign in spec was
released much to our relief
different tack
some of the early RCs for EAI were published
and
toward the end of last year EAI's email
address
e-mail address
internationalization
and the idea is you been able to send around
text in Japanese and so forth there
were hacks even have domain names in Japanese
but you couldn't have an e-mail
address
in Japanese
the EAI says
we want it to be
completely 100% international as
a whole
all through e-mail
a good thing
a lot of people don't realize
that the venerable RC twenty twenty
one and twenty two which
were the other internal specs for years were
actually just recently
updated
so the new numbers you have to memorize are
fifty three twenty one in fifty three twenty
two
this
I was the latest map that I could find so
pretty old back in 1999 Bill
Cheswick
produced this
this does not show the hosts
on the internet this shows the ISPs
on the internet
and I won't go into any more detail
and I don't recall what the
calling yes
so
let me get into this this year
probably messaging spam security and authentication
so lets talk about spamming a little.
I wasn't going to talk about spamming but
ever since I got here people in asking
me about it so there's still a lot of interest about it
obviously
the stand is arguably an economic issue the cost
to send
a message is far lower than the cost to receive
it
if this were true of
physical junk mail
then a dump mail truck would come up to my house every
day and just dump all the junk mail
off on my lawn
but it's not fortunately
notice that that possible misuse isn't necessarily
about
dollars or yen or anything like that
it's not currency it can be things like CPU time memory usage
human time etc
notice that every single thing we try to do
to protect ourselves from spam until this
point
has increased the cost to the receiver
so as we put in more and more antispam security what actually
move this function
to be more advantageous for the spammer
its a little strange
now there are a bunch of
possible approaches
there is of course
content filtering which is what
people normally do for example ninety days
and filters and so forth this is getting
pretty close to its limits and it doesn't
fix the crossfire
epostage which is what you really do
use some kind of money you can
attach it to each message
unfortunately needed any
pretty huge infrastructure to do all that
payment processing and
that's there's a lot of bickering on how to
do that
and acceptance problems. people don't
but it's always been afraid i refuse to pay anything
to send a message that
we're going to ask you to do
a tenth of a cent
hundredth of the cent promotes per message.
no no its too expensive. I can't afford it
that's a legitimate concerns about some elements
that sort of thing they're work around
challenge response is
popular
when you get mail from someone the never talked
to before you send them back challenge if they
would respond there's a human
being on the other hand what the bill through
unfortunately a lot of
people
get the challenges are spam and never replied
five thousand scale well it's particularly
bad for
automated systems that are trying to send out mail
like your bank
sending your bank statements
just don't respond well to that
challenge response
havshcash is
technique to do CPU
using time
CPU time memory
whatever
it's completely useless for Zombie farms because
they're not burning their own resources they're
burning
some victims resources so what's the point
gray listing is where you get a message from
somebody that you never seen before you
do a temporary failure on it
and wait for them to come back is there is
generally don't have a cue as a cue is
expensive
but it turns out they don't actually have
to have a cue because they don't change
the message very much that isn't it
he trying these things multiple times are
going back to keep track of what happened
before you just try multiple times if three
copies of their message gets through all the better
that
and on of course authentication that this
is the
if we know who actually sent the message
maybe we can hunt down and kill them
the
maybe not kill them
there's something a little less
that is insufficient by itself people go how
well what authenticated that's good right
well spammer can authenticate
as themselves
so you're saying it's authenticate it doesn't
mean it's still something you don't want to read
so
let me just talk about fish in the little
bit
fishing and spamming are not quite the same
thing although there's often
a lot of overlap
fishing is trying to track some money into
giving up some cards had a private information
too often to get a bank account information
or older than he needed to identity theft
it's not limited to do e-mail and it's not
the Nigerian or four nineteen spam was working
in physical mail
long before it hit the-mail I have personally
receive
those badly typed
letters
that were exactly of four elections than I
am and Nigerian dictator in these to get
a hundred million dollars out and you've been
identified as the trustworthy dot dot dot
pranksters have been preying on the elderly
as long as there have been elderly
so for none of this is new
that's true
basic forms of vision was one call your shop
and fishing which is really just
send out these things to enough people I hope
in some ways to promote the body
which works by the way unfortunately
are there still people think you can get something
for nothing
well what's being called spear fishing
he is actually pretty bad
this is where they actually spend a fair amount
of time researching an individual
they do a custom-made
message
I have received some of these things that
for example claim to be from the IRS saying that
so no I didn't
something earlier about this them
some of them
with some of our forms somewhere and it has
leader urgent that we contact some so immediately
or else
then the forced
we're actually were
forced to freeze all of our bank accounts
and so forth they know who I am and also with the company
not a thing that people will do it is %uh
people throw away
but bank saying some things that have the
last four digits of your account number on
it
which is perfectly safe because they don't
have a whole credit card number
well I'm wrong that right
all that out dumpster no I didn't
they send you a letter claiming to be from
your
%uh credit card prior
they have the last four digits of your account
number to give you exactly the same information
that you're legitimate
credit card company would
and
that's a lot easier to trick people
they can't stand significant money
talking to someone
so up
one other thing about the fishing know which
is
but the cracker what I just described attackers
lot of Harvard be
pretend to be someone you trust
an authentication can actually help with that
if it claims to be from one bank and would
not from my bank
and we're done
there's really two forms of authentication
and the standards
I'm not stand ready an FBI forms of half days
plus which is where where you look
our message across to you whose sending
they're sending the message to you and is
it possible that they would be sending a message
claiming to be from my bank
they were signature base which is where you
do
he's public encryption to do put digital signature
on the message
I mean there are these
authenticate users a lot of the key domains
because of the key management problems
and both of them can authenticate malicious
messages so this
not perfect
it did him in
potentially the cold war
consistently if we could get
Bob the entire network
to never mind your message
I wish probably can happen in hundred years
or so
I didn't get a talk show on this you know
who wants to be the first person sons message
well
we expected the recipients would want that
because they want to protect themselves but
it turns out has been descenders like the banks
they have really really been pushing us
plus some of the forward looking
places like Google
have been using DKIMand of the SP
up for some time
one important thing
for a transition period
you have to
allow unsigned mail to come in
because that's the way it's always been
and he can't just bring the world that we've
moved in
we will never have
another flag day on the internet like that
and just can't happen at this point
so what you'd like is for a the banks and
to be able to somehow tell you I signed all
my message is so if you
but if you get an unsigned message that claims
to be for me it's not for me
interior up argument signed in Paris is eight
the SP
and this is very controversial and still
stuck in the working group
I want to emphasize that
evacuations is not
because members can authenticate
and we can't leave it to humans either because
of things like cousin domains
but he had a Ebay billing was a famous one
that was not associate with
the bay in any way
and was trying to frighten people
so let me talk a little bit about the camera
which is what I've been working on mostly
I just wanted to specifications
one is the
the signature at the base standards which tells
how to sign and verified message
I've heard a lot of work and the other one
no one is the sign in practices which is how
to interpret on science messages on that one
has gotten laid down in the works
and at this point on
I walked away from it because
that's amazing
how many hours people can spend arguing about
the meaning of
relatively simple words
the way you can get away with it
is to use other DMS to destroy your
public he's since policies can indeed be public
you are rich off of this exist in the world
war
distributed database to get the keys out
this is a little unusual because normally
you don't have something that is so simple
to this
we do not by the way he serves we don't have
a assigning tree or anything like that it's
just to keep pair
because if you're asking
the purported Sendmail to give you the republican
or
reported sender
to give them
their home and he give you their publication
I mean
presumably contrast that
presumably
now there are people who
would like to put search
and investigators social security that probably
will go through some point
but it probably won't be necessary
with the the
I'm
possibility of theft of keys is one of the
nice ones is
if you get mail
they signed from a domain you don't know about
how do you know that that's a good omen were
not while reputation which I've got to
is the major approach but if you had
it's signed by someone that has served so
the key itself was signed by someone else
you could ask is that
and that gives you some of the reputation
is called of
%uh accreditation
and it sort of gives you the poor man's her
accreditation
%uh they're also of course the places that
wants to
I was moved towards first because they can't
make a living so on
as they think this is a fine idea is building
what was the
it really did do it obviously would
that's that's
what's the response
there is nobody there
yes
the you have built into your browser
Obama assures jurors that are prosperous should
say
Sonya forties that are trusted
it because you believe that they're not going
to start really signing one ski
exactly the same thing
think for a minute
the quality the city
yeah
the
you can first of all a matter of places that
would actually
make sure that you are legitimate but you
at least have a mailing address that really
works
that the people who claimed on the company
actually exists
simple things like that and somebody could
make a fair amount of money
the in certifying agency that
this is your views
to sign anything where they had check you
out for
they and there are places that do that for
the world as well but you're right some of
them are
in a tent lots of course inside turkey
sometimes it's not that expensive
%um
an hour to talk about signing practices unfortunately
it's got water down to the point where our
in my opinion it's not terribly useful in
or
so we're at the station is the usual way you
deal with that
the message too
I threw it out of the message comes from the
bagel in Dakar
okay because I've gotten their public he is
verify is so important step in mathematics
and cruel
provable
Joe I want to talk to he made a one dot com
don't believe them go on record on that one
and the usual approach his reputation what
we know about you being the one dot com
that reputation
it's been around for a long time
in the form of Diana's black homeless
as only negative reputation can say but it
remains good of the comoros a that
and of course
bad guys are switching around like he addresses
all time so
those lists are always tell
so in fact
helpful
but it's not actually all that great the main
event he gives you his
they a black hole
huge address bases that are
%um
for example dialogue but he
don't love
like the address this thing know nobody should
ever be sending
mail from those demands that don't go through
their providers mail services and that action
does help a lot
positive reputation on the other hand is really
hard to do
our because it breaks the world as we know
it
so right now there has been some sense a presumption
of innocence
when you receive email from so that you've
never seen it before well it might be would
you let me go
Spanish actor
so for but it might be legitimate
if you go to a world where you looked out
and say well if they have no
known reputation
there is probably bad think it's probably
a stammer as the jury
you know thousand
I can remember what the
number is ours
thousands of new domain stumble
online every day
first anniversary exists only for a day or
so and then they go away
to send a lot of the middle of the day
so
how does does a small player join the club
without having a positive reputation to begin
with the legitimate small player
this is
still a months old pro
we may end up going to a closed society
if you don't have somebody to introduce to
you
then
you can't get your mail for
%uh this is actually been true in human society
for a long long time so it's not the end of
the world but it does have some
unfortunate
implications and there's going to have to
be exceptions sales tax
anything that Tom Foley is going to want to
reject mail from people that heard of before
about I will point out challenge responses
of a chance to
this is to create a closed society
we have
attacks in their house
if you will a proven true test to try and
see if there's a human being on the other
end of the line
as a lot of places that would love to do it
credit nation
which is where they'll say
how about for you
for a fee
even having the base of money
does have value because they have to give
it credit card number
and it has to go through the crack of service
in your
essentially
one emerging off the
credit cards
companies work on reputation
well I don't know
the possibility
the likelihood of
stolen credit cards
what a lot of people say it as well you know
we
why don't we just
here's another media messages
yes well as a messenger who doesn't have spent
all that's why I did it get
message is pretty much every day from so and
so sexy teenage foxy girls
morning to get it wrong with me
Collins then as it's called
on is has been a problem for a while it is
doing that
yeah
authentication helps
but it's just too easy to get
all social networking storage tank was the
problem will just use
social networking
and use that for all or up
e-mail and in so you've got to be a friend
of mine
well it turns out has recently there's been
a lot of publicity
of worms in virus is that going to
%uh my face and Facebook and
what not an issue
you are you will accidentally
sanders down to your friends
it would generally come from you
and so they
are more likely to trust you so what is actually
almost
works
them
the male staffer
and it's this
on internet telephony spam spam over internet
it taught me
on his was just placed a growth industry
I wish is going to get
unbelievably bad
sometime soon
so some speculations on the future here that
these are speculations my opinion
I can't justify the runway
miss first term
I think we will get
some authenticated mail out there
%uh there will be some center reputation and
we'll roll
with time it will grow as quickly as i'd like
they've done it will
happen and it will start to grow
and it will be useful in only
because when you can get of not people
authenticated and they have good reputation
the probability that the other male is then
goes us the and actually
Tarnoff use them filters sensitivity
so if you will it will be a
well why didn't he was around
existence of them soldiers not something that
is this by itself
all we will see movement toward e-mail address
internationalization once again is going to
be relatively slow
the reason for that is because there's a part
of our problem not which is downgrading
a message for men
in our national life
Mel which by the way
what they're looking at it saying we're going
to use you Sheila Tate
for everything we're talking to declare the
characters that we just
he issued yesterday
with low vision done years ago
Bob that
taking AZT a great message and downgrading
them soon ask the message it is
almost impossible
and I did
and that's important
the daylights tensions in to send them all
and release them yet
try to do the downgrading and finally came
to the conclusion that there's certain things
we just have to guess
and you might not guess right all the time
so my inclination to say
I will not allow downgrading
the FAA on the message will bounce back me
up set down great message to begin with that
will slow adoption
the people young people in particular are
moving off of us and to keep this now we're
going into things like playing on people's
walls and Facebook
polymarker warnings investigating
so forth that is going to continue
take pot
a lot of people say
partially because people them
moving on to these things that are said to
be is that
but I think that indeed he is dead
what would that send to AP
as and he's not going away
a lot of reasons
are some things that could be dealt with this
one of the big proposals is to switch from
a portion or all of the-mail where
the center
connects to the recipient
this year's the male take it
to uphold
model where the recipient just sends a short
message to have male for you here and then
the
recipient
polls back for it
when it's convenient for them to do so
that does show that the cost function
so the %uh
the center actually has to
have some of
infrastructure there they have to be prepared
to use the word was mail
that's not true
he's still going to be in the essence the
structure I think
the essentially is a sensible and can do almost
anything with the exceptions it's going to
be good enough
for a long time
I think
in the medium term we will succeed in getting
the GSA absolutely everywhere
that's about the only people who have to ask
the e-mail will be
the people who listen to peace are rich and
other pressures and they can't go out and
upgrade the
of so I I'm pretty optimistic on that
and
most e-mail is going to end up being opposed
to the providers
it's gotten so much harder to run in this
juror
now than it was twenty years ago or ten years
ago were you
five years ago for a lot of reasons
the gallery reasons for example
there's a lot of new laws that apply to the
mail and retention and so forth
you really don't want to push that off onto
somebody else who can worry about it so
lots of companies for example who used to
run the Romanov's jurors
are moving to Jeanette
and I think you'll see
more of that I think you'll see a lot
more of that
I don't think we'll get to the
place where there are three companies in the
entire world that
have-mailboxes
although there would actually be certain advantages
to that
they won't get any more like that but
of small companies
don't want to deal with that
so some larger thoughts
%uh casual messaging well and he continued
to move away from essence few days now
you see more and more start going through
this book
%um %um
more and more self-government arrangements
again
people forty eight
instant gratification
and I am give somebody a man told us
he also sits there with mobile usage and
is there anyone in this room who is not secure
and one of these
anyone who wants to admit that their letter
I didn't think so
I e-mail is not going to die
on this
been predicted that that's just not true
it's to us into business
it's to a lawsuit in places where you can
really yes and water message
you have to think about what you're saying
for the standard
%uh it's the if you got
security and regulatory issues up
there are real problems with instant message
in
one of the things is it totally artificial
is that tax to have some us
I saw a lot of money in a light two cents
attacks
constant so companies as euro
to do that effectively zero when they put
this cost on it and they're making
fortune
off of that
and that will be enough people say I don't
want to pay a tenth of a cent for e-mail but
there will end soon
the two sides for anathema us
this is crazy
I'm hoping that won't go away
the other thing is that as you get into the
business world were more you're dealing with
people across time zones
%uh when you're a hacker
and you're up around the clock ticking away
that's not such a big deal but when we start
to get into the more conventional world actually
kind of the monarchy
and you get married you have kids
he started
go on to a more conventional schedule
that distinction
that's what you know
he's investigating
and even voice he's going to be were it's
already boring as it were and more than that
I actually were talking about that
of little bit in the last one
and I think there's a lot of very interesting
work to be done again the computer human interface
of the-mail
right now the-mail
but e-mails started off as a in box here
Carol Millhouse you go through them
it's gotten to the point where it's sort of
like it down secretary him to sort out the
junk mail
and give you the rest of it
e-mails should be news of New York should
say he messaging
is there any light eight
really the executive and then
who knows what it is you're doing can deal
with
and that is so rotten that stuff that you
actually cancer this stuff
where is not
a difficult time
who can sort of the things into an order and
say this is the most important thing for you
to deal with right now
your mind you know when someone for meeting
is coming up
who will
you know when
you call a meeting and people have responded
will go off and and
do you know about it
etc, etc.
there's a huge amount of work that can happen
here
what scares me is unified message in almost
a month or
too many messaging services in applications
out there
well I think there's too much
overlap and there's not enough compatibility
I want to show you a little chart that I made
up
just lost couple days
all of the services in applications on the
stars are ones by personal use
just run through this week or two
we start with Haiti and it
originally started out as an ally and application
it does I am really does that somehow some
lawyers Roosevelt for Israel
bosses from the board life where I think also
for him or whatever it does have its own address
book
the hum
right
on or is it was designed originally as a up
of course acquisitions
but it's not a all right and wrong headed
it's kind of a deal now
it will called for him
%um
for additional money
you can't do that by definition is that
for additional monies was time for a little
in the case
money changes hands
you know that's a nice for income in or outgoing
calls so I am
outgoing start flying but no in coming
strike one
well lawyers which was up from Seoul a couple
of days ago was called grand central
%uh Harris
mister President
for its part is not but the no three there
is that there are other this who was talk
as well
and so in some sense is closely related so
that's kind of the US
because unless the masses those two boys
it doesn't invade year old yes
Bobbie
that's a incoming calls
in fact that's the whole point
who was
you can do and how going
calls in the US yet to take action if you
want to do international outgoing calls
%um
he did not have a call for him
no that's what it was designed to do and recently
he can actually called for not just to of
regular phone number on what's called a PSA
and
up
public's something telephone network
%um
sorry I should know that
so that's what you have
that kind of remark you're no longer couldn't
find it
it can also go to Portland numbers in Texas
I don't want to count and there's no way to
call him from a regular telephone
but in fact when some told him for it to you
so
%uh which is
what I'm using
well let me get to
brought Boris is a service of had for a while
it's just the four okay
sir I was
I did
only those boys
okay does have an incoming calls
and of course you always get more on that
and also I said that number of local number
in the UK which were inspired Tony Birtley
on for a very serious sewers some for anything
you can see there
and it does
coming up phone calls
yes well I just heard plan was recently if
they saw
I'm I have it on this mission here
it's got I am still has some thoughts
it's not for us
but it does have video
for additional not even to incoming and outgoing
calls
but those are three
except for incoming board calls
so that's kind of another thing he can do
Cole Porter N
it does have a voice-mail
the and why everything here is that it's all
a matter of book
which by the way are in general not integrated
with one another so you have to have
one address
contacted you want to have happen
five or six for a and return address book
and of course I shall I use primarily because
then you scream saying
to know about my mom
when she has a problem and I don't want to
drive up your house
%uh on by will go into all of these details
is the know
there's almost no immigration on adverse book
which is a disaster
these things overlap in major ways
I've got it
a Google voice number now that came forward
sue my laptop live on the road but it also
brings it home
but I don't have a way to get that UK
number
to follow me around even though I'd like to
it's like a person getting immigration going
properly out
and what you have today is
in the mind message in
you have any clothes
of this
where they were were around in the day
don't know
that's where you know
Peres would look like that was an original
e-mail
are a real legitimate email address
yeah
I didn't forget percent couldn't figure out how to
put that in there
that
it could be from Texas
I I'm going to talk him into it
some groups who is advertising here if you're
interested in the e-mail message in
the conference on the melody spam is coming
up in July and mountain view
take a look at the web site
thank you very much and are there any questions
I answered everything
a lot of so-called
you're so long
okay what is without doubt
a little early for policy then I will be around
on the rest of the day
a few
what they're asking thing also
the IRS
I was not something I was doing I started
off with the initial design
of parents
how close are slim
was working on it
we concluded
at the company
that sent a text was not going to be
significantly better than Postfix and it
certainly wasn't going to be ready anytime
since close as eight
great voter
but hes very
careful
that means he's not
really all that clear
and so we look at it and said
worth it to us to do this he is remanded
and there on the line
I think it's insider and she a one-dot or
her
the
and ETA one dot org I don't remember
which and so you can download it but I don't
know about
certainly he's working on that now
as I just said by the way I'm working on some
stuff in Sendmail eight mostly stuff like
the IRS tensions what I don't know when or
if that's going to get released
why is not a priority for the company right
now
and
all of them so I'm hoping to do is to a private
release outflow
do not use this under any circumstances
etc kind of
release
but we'll see
so the question is who owns the market
that so there's two things there one it is
don't have any steps on all what
it's often e-mail servers are using
that information there used to be some
places that
did and publish it for free
but they have started
charging money for it
a lot of money for
and I'm so
so I don't have anything really recent but
from what I can determine piecing together
on Sendmail is still the largest
and she a in terms of America
numbers out there are leave of
Microsoft number two
what is
senate although it is a problem
thirty percent
something like that in my interest also around
of
maybe twenty percent of that everyone else
breaks up the
fifty percent so
on the other hand but
I'm afraid that's
speculative speculation and tribulations
%um
the second question is can we use in essence
you're doing
well we're just MTV's to improve the situation
yes I'd love to do that
there was a time when that would have been
easier for me when
when really seventy percent of the network
according to send mail and they mostly upgraded
fairly quickly
I no longer have that kind of leverage
people have gotten much more reluctant to
upgrade the rail sir
now I can't talk the visa into doing it
too
then we might actually have something
we were in a state like Utah Microsoft int doing it
yeah that's likely
the window of opportunity could be close
and once again I would love to do that
but he is just not
I I I do work for commercial companies not
reasonable for them to pay me to do that right
now it's not a priority
and so I can't do it on my own
that would like
I am doing some stuff on my own but there
are limits to what I can do a very old and
I was twenty five years ago
so that and can no longer pull those all nighters
every night for a week
any other questions
silence all right
thank you very much